Self Study Reports Collection UA050
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Self Study Reports Collection
1955 -- 2003
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Tufts University
School of Dental Medicine
UA050
2.0 Linear Feet 4 boxes
8 Volumes
Arrangement
This collection is organized in one series.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains reports and self-evaluations for the New England Association for Schools and Colleges and the Commission for Dental Accreditation of the American Dental Association.
Biographical / Historical
Self-study reports are used in many accreditation processes as a way for institutions to document their own programs in order to assist reviewing bodies in determining whether those programs meet the criteria for approval. The Office of Institutional Research maintains a list of associations, agencies, and government bodies that accredit, approve, and license Tufts University and its programs, along with those programs' accreditation status. Among them are the New England Association for Schools and Colleges and Commission for Dental Accreditation of the American Dental Association.
The New England Association for Schools and Colleges (NEASC) was founded in 1885 by Charles William Eliot, President of Harvard University, as a professional organization to assess and ensure the quality of institutions of higher education. NEASC supports educational institutions in maintaining these high standards through a self-evaluation and peer review process. Prior to 1971, NEASC was known as the New England Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools. In 2018, NEASC underwent a corporate restructuring process to comply with the United States Department of Education's mandate that its higher education commission (CIHE) operate as a "separate and independent entity." As a result, the CIHE operates as the New England Commission of Higher Education (NECHE), while the organization continues as NEASC.
Tufts University has been accredited by NEASC since 1929, and this status applies to the entire institution. NEASC requires member institutions to undergo regular evaluations, as well as a full accreditation visit at least once every ten years.
The Commission for Dental Accreditation of the American Dental Association (CODA) was established in 1975, in response to the American Dental Association's Council on Dental Education's recognition of the need for communities to have more direct representation in the accreditation process. Prior to that, the Council on Dental Education was the accrediting agency. CODA is the only body able to accredit post-secondary dental and dental-related educational programs for the United States Department of Education. The Dental Education program at Tufts has been accredited since 1945. CODA-accredited programs undergo periodic reviews, typically once every seven years.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research.
Administration and Governance -- Accreditation; Administration and Governance -- Planning, evaluation, policies & procedures
- Self-Study reports, 1955 -- 2003; 1976 -- 1985; UA050.001; 2.0 Linear Feet; 8 Volumes
  Scope and Contents
  This collection contains reports and self-evaluations for the New England Association for Schools and Colleges and the Commission for Dental Accreditation of the American Dental Association.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Self-Study Reports, 1960 -- 1992; UA050.001.001
    - Tufts self-study, 1960; UA050.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    - Self-evaluation for Title IX (Part 1 of 2), 1976; UA050.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
    - Self-evaluation for Title IX (Part 2 of 2), 1976; UA050.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
    - Self-study for reevaluation, 1904 -- 1982; UA050.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
    - School of Dental Medicine, Self-Study Manual, Volume II (Part 1 of 3), 1985; UA050.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
    - School of Dental Medicine, Self-Study Manual, Volume II (Part 2 of 3), 1985; UA050.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
    - School of Dental Medicine, Self-Study Manual, Volume II (Part 3 of 3), 1985; UA050.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
    - Self-Study Report for Comprehensive Visit by the New England Association of Schools and Colleges, 1992; UA050.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
      Visit: March 8-11, 1992
  - Reports for Commission on Dental Accreditation, American Dental Association, 1985; UA050.001.002
    - School of Dental Medicine Course Outlines Prepared for Commission on Dental Accredition, American Dental Association, 1985; UA050.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
    - School of Dental Medicine, General Practice Residency Program Prepared for Commission on Dental Accredition, American Dental Association, 1985; UA050.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
    - School of Dental Medicine, Advanced Specialty in Endodontics, Prepared for Commission on Dental Accredition, American Dental Association, 1985; UA050.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
    - School of Dental Medicine, Advanced Specialty in Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, Prepared for Commission on Dental Accredition, American Dental Association, 1985; UA050.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
    - School of Dental Medicine, Advanced Specialty in Orthodontics, Prepared for Commission on Dental Accredition, American Dental Association, 1985; UA050.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
    - School of Dental Medicine, Advanced Specialty in Pediatric Dentistry, Prepared for Commission on Dental Accredition, American Dental Association, 1985; UA050.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
    - School of Dental Medicine, Advanced Specialty in Periodontology, Prepared for Commission on Dental Accredition, American Dental Association, 1985; UA050.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
    - School of Dental Medicine, Advanced Specialty in Prostodontics, Prepared for Commission on Dental Accredition, American Dental Association, 1985; UA050.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Carnegie-Tufts self study, 1955 -- 1958; UA050.001.003
    Report of self-study which took place between 1955-1958 and was sponsored by the Carnegie Corporation. It consists of three main parts: The final report, Appendices A and B to the Final Report, and Appendix C to the Final Report.
    - Carnegie Self-Study, final report of the Executive Committee, 1955 -- 1958; UA050.001.004.00001 (Box Volume 4)
    - Carnegie Self-Study, Appendix A-B, Pages 1-288, 1955 -- 1958; UA050.001.004.00002 (Box Volume 4)
    - Carnegie Self-Study, Appendix B, Pages 289-502, 1955 -- 1958; UA050.001.004.00003 (Box Volume 4)
    - Carnegie Self-Study, Appendix B, Pages 503-824, 1955 -- 1958; UA050.001.004.00004 (Box Volume 4)
    - Carnegie Self-Study, Appendix B, Pages 825-1192, 1955 -- 1958; UA050.001.004.00005 (Box Volume 4)
    - Carnegie Self-Study, Appendix C, 1-2, 1955 -- 1958; UA050.001.004.00006 (Box Volume 4)
    - Carnegie Self-Study, Appendix C, 3, 1955 -- 1958; UA050.001.004.00007 (Box Volume 4)
    - Carnegie Self-Study, Appendix C, 4, 1955 -- 1958; UA050.001.004.00008 (Box Volume 4)
  - Self-Study reports, 1985 -- 2003; UA050.001.004
    - Self Study Report to the New England Association of Schools and Colleges, 2003; UA050.001.005.00001 (Box 5)
    - Self-Study Manual vol. I, Part I, 1985; UA050.001.005.00002 (Box 5)
    - Self-Study Manual vol. I, Part II, 1985; UA050.001.005.00003 (Box 5)
    - Self-Study Manual vol. I, Part III, 1985; UA050.001.005.00004 (Box 5)
    - Institutional Self-Study Report, 1985; UA050.001.005.00005 (Box 5)